<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Perfinion's Blog</title><link>http://blog.perfinion.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://blog.perfinion.com/tag/gentoo/feed/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 12:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><item><title>SELinux userspace 2.6 released</title><link>http://blog.perfinion.com/2016/10/selinux-userspace-26-released/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The SELinux userspace libraries and programs recently released version 2.6. I
bumped them in Gentoo a couple days ago. They add a ton of new features, here
are a few of the main points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got semanage and sepolicy updated to use setools4. Setools4 replaces
setools3 which has been unmaintained for quite a long time and had issues with
the new policy versions. If you previously had &lt;code&gt;policy-version = 29&lt;/code&gt; in your
&lt;code&gt;/etc/selinux/semanage.conf&lt;/code&gt;, you can comment it out after updating to
app-admin/setools-4.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;genhomedircon has a ton of updates. I added new templating patterns that are
expanded for usernames and ids. I added support for &lt;code&gt;%{USERNAME}&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;%{USERID}&lt;/code&gt;
to expand in fcontexts. This was primarily for &lt;code&gt;$XDG_RUNTIME_DIR&lt;/code&gt; adding
&lt;code&gt;/run/user/%{USERID}&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;genhomedircon finally has support for %group syntax in the list of users. You
can now do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;semanage login --add -s staff_u -r &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;s0-s0:c0.c1023&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;%wheel&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of having to hardcode all the admins usernames. This is something I'd
wanted for ages but didn't get around to, so thanks a ton to Gary for this.
Once this has all gone stable I'll look into adding this automatically to
seusers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;genhomedircon now replaces the whole context instead of only the user part.
This means genhomedircon can support RBACSEP now. This is role-based separation
instead of UBAC like we currently have in gentoo. UBAC has some limitations
about switching users that RBACSEP can would be able to fix. Because of this,
entries mapped to the default user and system_u are no longer special-cased.
This fixes an issue if a user had a homedir that was not in /home the fcontexts
would be missing. There is another side effect of this fix, there is now a
warning printed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;libsemanage.add_user: user system_u not in password file
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is caused by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# semanage login -l&lt;/span&gt;
system_u    system_u    s0-s0:c0.c1023    *
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The warning is non-fatal and doesn't actually cause any problems. It is because
system_u is not a valid Linux user so the line is nonsense. I will remove this
line from seusers in the policy when I add %wheel. If you want to make the warning go away now, you can run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;semanage login --delete system_u
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is also a pcre2 USE-flag for using libpcre2 instead of libcpre. The
default is still pcre1 because pcre2 takes up more disk space in the
file_contexts.bin files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full announcement email is &lt;a href="https://marc.info/?l=selinux&amp;amp;m=147646050027049&amp;amp;w=2"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason Zaman</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 12:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>tag:blog.perfinion.com,2016-10-30:2016/10/selinux-userspace-26-released/</guid><category>security</category><category>gentoo</category></item></channel></rss>